So welcome back.
欢迎回来。
It's a great honor to introduce a mathematical legend.
有幸介绍一位数学传奇人物。
John Milnor, who as an undergraduate showed that the integral of the curvature of a knot
John Milnor，在本科期间证明了纽结曲率的积分
was at least four pi, and became very famous as a result,
结果至少为四π，并因此而非常著名，
won the Fields Medal at the age of 31, was professor at Princeton and the Institute for Advanced Study,
在31岁时获得了菲尔兹奖，曾在普林斯顿大学和高等研究院任教，
and is now director of the Center for Mathematical Research at Stony Brook,
现在是石溪数学研究所的主任，
and is a recipient of many honors, including the National Medal of Science,
并且获得过许多荣誉，包括国家科学奖章，
We'll introduce the next speaker.
我们将介绍下一位演讲者。
Jack Milnor, go ahead.
Jack Milnor，请发言。
Well, it's a great pleasure to introduce Vladimir Voevodsky.
非常荣幸地向大家介绍 Vladimir Voevodsky。
Voevodsky began his mathematical career in Moscow, and then came here to Harvard as a junior fellow,
开始他的数学生涯在莫斯科，然后作为初级研究员来到哈佛，
and after a few years at Northwestern, is now at the Institute for Advanced Study.
在西北大学工作几年后，现在在高等研究院。
And as you all know, he was recently awarded a Fields Medal for his work on motivic homotopy theory.
而你们都知道，他最近因为对母题同伦论的工作获得了菲尔兹奖。
This is a marvelous development which introduces ideas and methods from homotopy theory into pure algebra,
这是一个美妙的发展，它将同伦理论的思想和方法引入纯粹代数，
and gives an essential new tool for solving algebraic problems.
为解决代数问题提供了必不可少的新工具。
So it's a great pleasure to introduce Voevodsky.
所以很荣幸介绍 Voevodsky。
Hello, thank you very much for, thank you, Jack, for the introduction.
你好，非常感谢 Jack 的介绍。
So I was given by Arthur sort of an impossible task.
我被 Arthur 给了几乎不可能完成的任务。
I was requested to explain motivic homotopy theory so that it will be understood by non-mathematicians.
要求我解释母题同伦论，使其能够被非数学家理解。
So whatever came out of it, you'll see now,
所以你们现在将会看到结果。
but I don't guarantee that it will be now understandable by either mathematicians or non-mathematicians.
但我不保证这现在对数学家或非数学家来说都能理解。
So what there was at first, so at first there were spaces.
所以最初的情况是，一开始有空间。
So mathematicians were studying spaces and starting with simple examples of spaces.
所以数学家研究空间，并从简单的空间例子开始。
So one of the most basic spaces is a point.
最基本的空间之一是一个点。
There is one which is even more basic, but it's hard to draw.
还有一个更基本的，但很难画出来。
Another one is standard space, which I will have to talk about, is a unit interval.
另一个标准空间，我将不得不讨论的是单位区间。
So an interval of the real line, a line between 0 and 1.
所以实数线上的一个区间，在0和1之间的一条线段。
The third example here on the picture is some example of a space of dimension 2.
图片中的第三个例子是一个二维空间的例子。
It's supposed to look like some baking good with two holes in it.
它应该看起来像一个有两孔的烘焙食品。
So the last example is more sophisticated, and I want to include it here.
最后一个例子更复杂，我想把它包括进来。
It's a more sort of mathematical example of a space.
这是一个更数学意义上的空间例子。
It's a space of all n by n matrices with complex entries and with non-zero determinant.
这是一个所有 n 乘 n 的复矩阵构成的空间，并且行列式非零。
That would be a sophisticated space of dimension n, well,
那将是一个复杂的 n 维空间，好，
depending on how you count, n square or 2n square.
取决于你如何计数，是 n 平方或 2n 平方。
So there are many different axiomatizations of the notion of a space in mathematics.
在数学中，有许多不同的空间公理化概念。
For instance, there are topological spaces, there are metric spaces.
比如说，有拓扑空间，有度量空间。
At the end, it all doesn't matter.
最终，这并不重要。
As long as one only considers non-pathological examples,
只要只考虑非病态的例子，
it all comes to the same thing.
它们最终都是一样的。
So I will assume that there is some intuitive understanding of what space is.
因此我将假设对空间的概念有一些直观的理解。
That such understanding is present.
这样的理解是存在的。
So any space, if you formalize it, really write down a definition,
所以任何空间，如果你形式化它，真正写下定义，
it will be a tremendously infinite object.
它将是一个极其无穷的对象。
So it's very difficult to work with.
因此很难处理。
So to distinguish spaces mathematically, we use what we call invariance.
为了在数学上区分空间，我们使用所谓的不变量。
So something more understandable, more finite, typically,
因此一些更易于理解、更有限的东西，
than the space itself associated to a space.
比该空间本身通常要多。
So there are two invariants which I will dare to call the most fundamental ones.
所以有两个不变量我敢称之为最基础的。
One is the dimension of a space.
其中一个是空间的维数。
So we have dimension zero for a point and dimension one for the interval.
我们有维度为零的点和维度为一的区间。
And another invariant is the number of pieces the space consists of.
另一个不变量是空间由多少部分组成。
So in this picture, again, the point consists of one piece.
所以在这个图中，点仍然由一个部分组成。
You cannot divide it into two disconnected pieces.
你不能将其分成两个不连通的部分。
And then there is something below the point which is sort of a deformed circle
点下方有一些变形的圆圈，
with some deformed interval sitting inside,
其中有某个变形的区间嵌在里面，
but it consists of two different pieces, two disjoint pieces.
但它由两部分不同且不交的部分组成。
There's a circle and there's an interval.
有一条圆和一条区间。
So the number of pieces is another invariant of a space.
所以部分的数量是空间的另一个不变量。
Typically, when one thinks of a space,
通常，当人们想到一个空间时，
one thinks of a space which has only one piece.
他们想到的是只有一个部分的空间。
But that's just a custom.
但这只是一种习惯。
So what is homotopy theory about?
所以同伦理论主要研究什么呢？
What it does, it basically studies...
它所做的，基本上是研究...
Oh, I need to say something.
哦，我需要说一些事情。
Let's call pi zero over space the set of its pieces.
我们可以称空间上的 π₀ 为该空间的组成部分集合。
So if space has two pieces, then pi zero is a set of two elements,
因此，如果空间有两个部分，那么 π₀ 就是一个包含两个元素的集合，
namely these pieces.
即这些部分本身。
So it's typically much more finite than the space itself.
它通常比空间本身要有限得多。
What homotopy theory does, it studies some fancy versions of this invariant,
同伦理论研究这个不变量的一些复杂版本，
which are called higher homotopy sets.
这些被称为高次同伦集。
Now, I will try to explain how one gets to these pi n's,
现在，我将尝试解释如何得到这些 πₙ，
where pi n will be some set for any integer n,
其中 πₙ 将是某个集合，对于任何整数 n，
for any, excuse me, non-negative integer n,
对于任何，抱歉，非负整数 n，
how one gets to pi n from pi zero.
从 π₀ 如何得到 πₙ。
The first thing which I need to...
首先我需要...
It can be done in different ways.
可以用不同的方法来做。
So I choose to base my explanation on the notion of a continuous map,
所以我选择基于连续映射的概念来解释，
which will also play a fundamental role further.
这个概念将在以后发挥重要作用。
So what is a continuous map?
那么什么是连续映射？
So I have a space.
我有一个空间。
This I cannot show on the projection.
这在投影上无法显示。
I have a space n, m, and a space n.
我有一个 n,m 空间，和一个 n 空间。
And a map from one to another is any rule
从第一个空间到另一个空间的映射是任意规则
which assigns to point of the first space
它将第一个空间中的点
and point of the second space.
和第二个空间中的点指定。
The easiest way, of course, to understand it
当然，最容易理解的方式
is by looking at examples.
是通过看例子。
And the idea that it's continuous means
而它连续的意思是
that if something was close,
如果某物靠近，
then it doesn't get too far apart.
那么它不会相差太远。
So let's denote by c of m, n
所以我们用 c(m, n) 表示从 m 到 n 的所有连续映射的集合。
the set of all continuous maps from m to n.
并且我们再次通过例子来说明它是什么。
And we'll see again, by example, what it is.
如果我考虑从一个点到任何空间的连续映射，
If I'm looking at continuous maps
那么从一个点到一个空间的映射是什么呢？
from a point to any space,
它仅仅由这个唯一点映到哪里决定。
so what is a map from a point to a space?
所以从一个点到一个空间的映射
It's just determined by where this unique point goes.
就相当于这个空间中的一个点。
So a map from a point to a space
因此，从一个点到任何空间的映射集合
is the same as a point on this space.
与这个空间中的点集是一致的。
So the set of maps from the point to any space
(已与上一条字幕合并)
is just a set of points of this very same space.
这只是一个空间中点的集合。
Another example is what is the set of maps
另一个例子是任何空间到一个点的映射集是什么？
from any space to a point?
从任意空间到一个点？
There's only one place for all the points
第一空间的所有点只能去一个地方，
of the first space to go,
即目标空间上的唯一一点。
namely this only point on the target space.
而从任意空间到这个点的映射只有一个。
And there's always only one map
所以这就是第二个例子。
from any space to the point.
这是一个更复杂的例子。
So that's example number two.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
Here is a more fancy example.
Let's look at maps
让我们看看从单位区间
from the unit interval,
到任意空间的映射，
the interval of the real line,
实数线上的区间，
to any space.
到任何空间的映射。
So it will have some beginning
所以它会有一个起点
where the point zero goes
其中点零被映射到
or point one goes,
或者点一被映射到，
and then there will be all the points
然后所有介于零和一之间的数字会被映射到所有的中间点。
where all the numbers between zero and one go.
因此，它是连续映射。
So the fact that it's a continuous map
(已与上一条字幕合并)
means that this gadget will have no breaks in it.
这意味着这个装置不会有断点。
That's what it intuitively means.
这就是它的直观含义。
So the set of all continuous maps
所以从区间到任意空间的所有连续映射
from the interval to any space
就是一个空间内的路径集合。
is just a set of paths inside this space.
现在让我们回到空间连通分支的概念。
Now let's go back to the notion
我们如何正式地说两个点属于同一个连通分支？
of the number of pieces of a space.
当两点位于同一个连通分支时，
How can we say formally
(已与上一条字幕合并)
when two points lie in the same piece?
So if they lie in the same piece,
(已与上一条字幕合并)
then they can be connected by a path.
然后它们可以通过一条路径连接。
In different pieces,
在不同的部分，
there's no way you can find a path
你无法找到一条不中断的路径
without breaks which connects one point to another.
将一个点连接到另一个点。
So to define formally
因此为了正式定义
what it means for two points to belong to the same piece,
两点属于同一部分的意义，
one can use this notion of a path,
可以使用路径的概念，
of a continuous map from interval to the space.
即从区间映射到空间的连续映射。
So let me repeat myself again.
所以我再重复一遍。
So the only thing which one needs to know
因此唯一需要知道的是
to define the set pi zero of n,
要定义 π₀(n) 的集合，
the set of pieces,
该集合中的元素是各个部分，
is to know what are points and what are paths
就是要知道哪些是点，哪些是从这些点出发的路径。
between these points.
这些点之间的路径。
Well, this is a little bit more fancy,
嗯，这稍微有点复杂，
and maybe I'm not able to explain it as good.
我可能无法解释得特别好。
Now here I'm moving to the next invariant,
现在我转移到下一个不变量，
next homotopy set pi one.
下一个同伦群 π₁。
As I said, pi zero is the starting point
如我所说，π₀ 是一系列同伦群的起点。
of an infinite series of homotopy sets.
一系列同伦群。
So what one does for pi zero,
所以对于 π₀，
one takes points
一个取点，
and identifies sort of those
然后将那些可以通过路径连接的点视为相同。
which can be connected by a path.
现在我固定两个点 P 和 Q。
Now suppose I fix two points, P and Q.
现在让我们考虑所有连接它们的路径。
Now let's consider all the paths which connect them.
假设它们落在同一个连通分支上，
Suppose they land the same piece,
所以存在一条路径连接它们。
so there is some path which connects them.
让我们来看所有的路径。
Let's look at all paths.
因此我们得到一些路径空间，无论那是什么意思。
So we get some space of paths, whatever that means.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
Let's try to understand how many pieces
让我们尝试理解这个路径空间包含多少个部分
this space of paths has,
并且称这些部分的集合为我的原始空间相对于点P和Q的π₁
and call this set of pieces the pi one
于是实际上我们需要做的事情是
of my original space relative to points P and Q.
现在考虑从一个正方形到该空间的连续映射。
So in practice what one has to do
如果我有一个正方形映射到这个空间，
is to consider now continuous maps from a square.
而且假设我们要求这个映射
If I have a square mapping to the space,
完全将这条边收缩到点P
and let's say I request to have a map
并且完全将这条边收缩到点Q。
which contracts this side completely to point P
(已与上一条字幕合并)
and this side completely to point Q.
Then the image of this side will be a path
然后这个侧面的像将是一条从 P 到 Q 的路径
going from P to Q,
并且这个侧面的像也将是一条从 P 到 Q 的路径。
and the image of this side will also be a path
当我连续地从这个侧面移动到这个侧面，
which is going from P to Q.
我可以把它看作是路径之间的路径。
And as I move from this side to this side continuously,
所以这是一个路径之间的连续变形。
I can think of it as being a path between the paths.
因此它生成了...
So it's continuous deformation between the paths.
现在我可以考虑空间中路径片段的集合
So it generates...
的集合。
Now I can consider the set of pieces
(已与上一条字幕合并)
of the space of paths
where two paths are declared
如果两条路径可以由一个从正方形到空间的映射连接起来，则它们属于同一个部分。
to belong to the same piece
现在这是一个可以重复的过程，
if they can be connected by such a map from a square.
接着我可以使用立方体来连接正方形上的映射
Now this is a procedure which can be repeated,
以此类推，最终得到一系列集合
and then I can use cubes to connect maps from squares
这些集合被称为相对于空间同伦等价的集合。
and so on, and one gets a sequence of sets
现在...
which are called homotope sets over space.
哦，对不起，刚才我说的就是这个。
Now...
现在...
Well, I'm sorry, that's what I just said.
好吧，我抱歉，刚才说的就是这个。
There is one nice example which I want to give.
我想给出一个很好的例子。
If we try to define these homotope sets
如果我们尝试定义这些同伦集
for the space of complex matrices
对于非零行列式的复矩阵空间
with a non-zero determinant,
它是一个非常复杂的问题
it's, of course, a very complicated problem
如何比较这些同伦集
how to compare the homotope sets
与非零行列式的复矩阵空间
with the space of complex matrices
它是一个非常复杂的问题
with a non-zero determinant.
如何计算这样一个奇怪的空间中的如此奇怪的东西
It's, of course, a very complicated problem
然而，事实证明这是可以做到的
how to compute such a weird thing for such a weird space.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
However, it turns out that it can be done,
and the answer,
答案是，
at least when we consider matrices which are very, very big,
至少当我们考虑非常、非常大的矩阵时，
n by n, where n is very large,
阶矩阵，其中 n 很大，
the answer turns out to be wonderfully simple.
结果答案出奇地简单。
It's the first homotope set is the point.
第一同调群只是单点集。
Any two matrices can be connected by a path,
任意两个矩阵可以通过路径连接，
and there's only one piece in the whole space of matrices.
而在整个矩阵空间中只有一个部分。
If I consider paths,
如果我考虑路径，
then it turns out that the pieces in the space of paths
那么在路径空间中的部分
are numbered by integers.
由整数编号。
So pi 1 is a set of integers...
所以 π₁ 是整数集...
I'm sorry, did I...
对不起，我...
I made a mistake writing this page.
我在写这个页面时犯了一个错误。
It has to read like this.
它必须这样读。
Pi 0 is a star.
π₀ 是一个星号。
Or did I?
或者是我？
No, no, no, sorry.
不，不，不，对不起。
So pi 1 can be identified with the set of integral numbers.
所以 π₁ 可以与整数集等同。
Pi 2 is again just one point.
π₂ 再次只是一个点。
Pi 3 is again the set of integral numbers.
π₃ 再次是整数集。
And then it goes on like that for a very long time.
然后它会持续很长一段时间。
For how long exactly depends on number n over there.
到底持续多久取决于那边的 n。
But basically if n is infinity, then it goes on forever.
但基本上如果 n 是无穷大，那么它会永远持续下去。
And that's called what periodicity theorem.
这被称为周期性定理。
There was one of the very impressive achievements
在上世纪五六十年代早期，数学上取得了一项非常令人印象深刻的成绩。
of mathematics in early 60s, late 50s.
那是拓扑理论中最早的重大计算之一。
I don't know the history well enough.
我对历史了解不够深入。
But that was one of the really first big computations
但这是一项真正重要的重大计算。
of homotopy theory.
所以这就是我想说的关于同伦论的内容。
So that's what I wanted to say about homotopy theory.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
It studies spaces.
它研究空间。
It associates to them the homotopy sets,
它将这些空间关联到同伦集，
which come from studying paths of paths and so on.
这些同伦集来自于对路径的路径的研究等等。
And here is an example of computation.
而这里是一个计算的例子。
These are actually things which can be computed
实际上，在某些非平凡情况下，这些东西可以被计算出来。
in some non-trivial cases.
现在我想跳过一些内容，并在代数背景下做类似的事情。
Now I want to jump somehow and do something similar
所以只有一个方法来做这件事。
in algebraic setting.
我不知道今天我是否有足够的时间来讲述。
So there is only one way to do it.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
And I don't know how much I will have time to say today.
But there is one topic which I want to talk about very quietly
但有一个话题我想悄悄地谈论
and without hurry.
并且不急于进行。
So that's something which I never saw it even mentioned
这是我从未在任何关于数学的通俗书籍中看到过的内容。
in any popular book about mathematics.
我看到了代数方程被提及。
I saw algebraic equations mentioned.
我可能看到了同伦群被提及，
I saw homotopy groups probably even mentioned,
尤其是在拓扑学入门书籍中。
especially for elementary books in topology.
但我认为20世纪数学的核心
But I think that at the heart of 20th century mathematics
涉及一个特定的概念。
lies one particular notion.
那就是范畴的概念。
And that's the notion of a category.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
So let me try to explain what it is about.
所以让我试着解释一下。
So it's a very formal gadget.
这是一个非常形式化的装置。
And I will illustrate it by an example.
我将通过一个例子来说明它。
So here are two examples of categories.
所以这里有两类的例子。
Let's forget about the second one for a moment.
先暂时忽略第二个。
Just look at the first one.
只看第一个。
So here I have a picture of a category with three objects,
所以这里我画了一个有三个对象的范畴图，
A, B, C.
。
Now there are arrows between those objects,
现在这些对象之间有一些箭头，
which are called morphisms.
这些箭头叫做态射。
And then there is the rule, which says that if I have one arrow
然后有一个规则，说如果我有一个箭头
and then it's followed by another arrow,
然后它被另一个箭头跟随，
then there is a third arrow.
那么就会有一个第三个箭头。
Let's say if I have an arrow from A to B
假设我有一个从 A 到 B 的箭头
and arrow from B to C,
和一个从 B 到 C 的箭头，
then there is a rule to get from such a pair
那么就有规则可以从这样的配对
an arrow from A to C.
得到一个从 A 到 C 的箭头。
That's called the composition rule.
这被称为合成规则。
But let's even forget this third part for a second.
但让我们暂时忘记这个第三部分。
It's not necessarily important for intuitive understanding.
对直观理解来说，它不一定很重要。
Main thing which exists in categories
在范畴中主要存在的是对象和态射。
is that there are objects and there are morphisms.
对每个对象对，还有一个形式集合。
There is a formal set.
这个集合称为对象集。
In this case, the set of A, B, C,
在这种情况下，集合是 A, B, C，
which is called the set of objects.
称为对象集。
For every pair of objects,
对于每一对对象，
there is another formal set.
有一个另一个形式集合。
In this case, it's X and Y between A and B,
在这种情况下，它是 A 和 B 之间的 X 和 Y，
Z between B and C, and T between A and C,
B 和 C 之间的 Z，以及 A 和 C 之间的 T，
which are called morphisms between these objects.
这些称为这些对象间的态射。
Now the first example is an example
现在第一个例子是一个组合有限范畴的例子。
of a combinatorial finite category.
这里有一个第二个例子。
Here is a second example.
对象是空间，所有存在的空间。
Objects are spaces, all spaces which exist.
两个空间之间的态射是这些空间之间的连续映射。
Morphisms between two spaces
当然，连续映射可以复合。
are continuous maps between these spaces.
所以这给出了一个非常不同的范畴的例子。
And of course continuous maps can be composed.
而且对我个人来说有些令人惊讶的是
So that gives an example of a category
(已与上一条字幕合并)
of a very different kind.
And what was somewhat amazing for me personally
(已与上一条字幕合并)
and an amazing discovery is that almost,
令人惊讶的是，几乎对于很多类数学对象而言，
let's say for very many classes of mathematical objects,
让我们说对于大多数数学对象的类别来说，
there are natural categories which correspond to them.
存在自然的范畴与它们对应。
So for most classes of mathematical objects,
所以对于大多数数学对象的类别，
we can construct a category whose objects
我们可以构造一个范畴，
will be these objects.
其中的对象将是这些对象。
Morphisms will be some natural ways
态射将是将一种类型的对象连接到另一种类型的某些自然方式，
of connecting one object of this type to another,
并且将存在某种复合。
and there will be some kind of composition.
对不起。
Sorry.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
So here is a more formal way to see what a category is.
所以这里是一种更正式的方式来定义范畴。
So there is a set of objects.
有一个对象集合。
For any pair of objects, there is a set of morphisms
对于任意一对对象，存在一个态射集
from this object to, between these two objects.
从这个对象到这两个对象之间的某个对象。
And then there is some composition rule.
然后有一些复合规则。
Now, what I hope to do now is to show how such a,
现在我希望做的是展示这样一种，
well, let's see, how does it work?
好吧，让我们看看，它是如何工作的？
Why is it interesting?
它为什么有趣？
Let's, for instance, consider the category
比如，我们考虑拓扑空间范畴
of topological spaces.
是怎样的。
And let's take, let's choose a space N.
让我们选择一个空间 N。
What can we say about this space?
我们能说这个空间的什么呢？
Looking at it exclusively as being an object
仅从它作为一个空间范畴中的对象来看。
of the category of spaces.
因此我不打算看这个空间内部。
So I don't want to look inside of this space.
我对其内部一无所知。
I know nothing about its insides.
我只知道连续映射将这个空间
I only know continuous maps relating this space
关联到所有其他空间。
to all other spaces.
所以我们不是关注这个对象的结构，
So instead of looking on the structure of the object,
而是关注它的这种社会关系。
you look at his sort of social relationship.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
The very first example, can we figure out
这个非常简单的例子，当空间是一个点时我们能弄清楚吗？
when the space is a point?
当空间是点的时候？
To this, there is a nice answer.
对于此问题，有一个很好的答案。
When a space is a point, if and only if
当空间是一个点，当且仅当
for any other space, there is a single morphism
对于任何其他空间，存在唯一的态射
to this one.
到这个点。
So that characterizes the point completely,
这完全地、唯一地由到和从它的态射来表征。
exclusively by morphisms to and from it.
让我们问一个更复杂的问题。
Let's ask a more complicated question.
什么情况下一个空间 N 是连通的？
When is a space N connected?
(已与上一条字幕合并)
So when it consists of only one piece.
所以当它只由一个部分组成时。
Or more generally, can we somehow express,
或者更一般地，我们能否 somehow 表达，
let's say the very first homotopia set,
说第一个同伦集，
the set of pieces, purely in categorical terms?
部件的集合，纯粹用范畴论的语言？
It turns out that yes, we can.
结果是，我们可以。
So let's try to play this game.
所以让我们尝试玩这个游戏。
So first of all, we know what is the set of points
首先，我们知道空间中的点集
of the space.
是从点到这个空间的态射集。
It's the set of morphisms from the point to this space.
我们已经刻画了点。
And we have already characterized the point
(已与上一条字幕合并)
in some internal way.
以某种内部方式。
Now, let's consider the unit interval.
现在，我们考虑单位区间。
The set of maps from the unit interval, morphisms
单位区间到空间的映射集合，即态射集，是路径集合。
from the unit interval to the space, is the set of paths.
现在我需要知道路径的起点和终点是什么。
Now, I need to know what is the beginning of the path
为此，我需要态射复合的概念。
and what is the end of the path.
所以如果我有一条路径，那么单位区间上有两个特殊的点，0 和 1，
For that, I need the notion of a composition of morphisms.
它们是从点到单位区间的态射。
So if I have a path, I have two distinguished points, 0 and 1,
(已与上一条字幕合并)
on the unit interval, which are morphisms from the point
to the unit interval.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
If I look at the composition, my path composed
如果我查看复合路径，这条路径与其中一个点复合后，
with one of these points, I get a point of the space,
我得到空间中的一个点，这是路径的起点或终点。
which is the beginning or the end of the path.
因此仅使用范畴结构，
So using purely the structure of the category,
我知道哪些是点集。
I know what is the set of points.
我知道哪些是路径集。
I know what is the set of paths.
并且我知道如何给一条路径指定起点和终点。
And I know how to assign beginning and end to a path.
现在我可以说明组成部分的集合是什么了，
So now I can say what is the set of pieces,
因为我只是必须识别可以通过路径连接的两点，换句话说，
because it's simply I have to identify two points which
(已与上一条字幕合并)
can be connected by a path, in other words,
for which there is a path such that it's beginning and end.
其中有路径使得其起点和终点。
And that gives me the set pi 0.
这就给了我集合 π₀。
So the only thing which is here, which is not internal
所以这里唯一不在范畴内的是
to the category of categorical structure,
原子结构范畴内的东西，
is the unit interval itself.
就是单位区间本身。
We don't know how to characterize it from the inside.
我们不知道如何从内部对其进行描述。
But as soon as I have a category and something which
但只要我有一个范畴并且想要称呼这个单位区间为两个映射，
I want to call the unit interval with two maps,
A 和 B，分别称为起点和终点，
A and B, called beginning and end,
我就可以定义某种 π₀。
I can define some kind of pi 0.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
How good this definition will be?
这个定义会有多好？
It's a big question.
这是一个大问题。
So similarly, if I want to compute the next homotopy set,
所以同样地，如果我想计算下一个同伦集，
here I'm not going in that much detail.
在这里我不会详细展开。
But what I will need to know will be the object point,
但我需要知道的是对象点，
the object called unit interval.
称为单位区间的一个对象。
And then I'll need to know to have some distinguished object
然后我还需要知道一个特殊的对象
which is called the square.
它被称为正方形。
And some finite number of morphisms
连接这些对象的一些有限态射。
connecting these objects.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
As soon as I have such a purely combinatorial structure
一但我有了这样一个纯粹组合结构
inside my category, I can consider morphisms
在我的范畴内部，我可以考虑态射
with values in any object and get something which
值在任何对象上并得到一些东西
I will call pi 0 and pi 1.
我会称之为 π₀ 和 π₁。
I can continue that and model formally in any category.
我可以继续这样做并在任何范畴中形式化。
Basically, for what I'm talking about,
基本上，就我谈论的内容而言，
it's enough to understand pi 0.
理解 π₀ 就足够了。
And the rest is just not to look too elementary.
而其余部分只是不要太基础。
So one can formalize the situation
因此，可以形式化当有点、区间、正方形、立方体时的情况
when one has point, interval, square, cube,
的情形。
cube of the next dimension, and so on.
高一维的立方体，依次类推。
Now all these things in usual topological world
现在这所有的东西在通常拓扑世界中
map to each other.
互相映射。
There are two maps from the point to the interval,
从点到区间有两个映射，
the beginning and the end.
分别是开始和结束。
There are four maps from the interval to the square,
从区间到正方形有四个映射，
the four sides of the square.
正方形的四条边。
There are six maps from the square to the cube,
从正方形到立方体有六个映射，
the six sides of the cube, and so on.
立方体的六条边，依次类推。
They satisfy some relations.
它们满足某些关系。
So I can formally say, let's take any category whatsoever.
因此我可以正式地说，让我们取任意一个范畴。
Let's take a series of objects and morphisms between them,
让我们取一系列对象及其之间的态射，
satisfying appropriate conditions.
满足适当的条件。
Let's call such a gadget a cubical object.
我们可以称这样的装置为立方体对象。
So as soon as I have a cubical object in any category,
所以只要我在任何范畴中有一个立方体对象，
I can play the game which I sort of explained
我就可以玩我刚才解释过的游戏
for pi 0 and pi 1 and define some kind of homotopy sets
对于 π₀ 和 π₁ 并为此范畴中的其他对象定义某种同伦集。
for any other object in this category.
当然，需要说明的是，在大多数情况下
Of course, it needs to be said that in most cases
它可能不会很好地工作。
it's not going to work very well,
(已与上一条字幕合并)
but it will work somehow.
但它会以某种方式起作用。
Now let's go to the next...
现在让我们进入下一个...
So of course that was just an example.
当然，这只是个例子。
In principle, there are many more structures,
在原则上，还有许多更多的结构，
let's say in topological spaces,
比如拓扑空间中的，
which are needed for homotopy theory.
对同伦理论来说是必需的。
So one can translate most of the structures
因此可以将大多数结构
into categorical terms,
转换成范畴论的语言，
as I tried to show in this example of cubical spaces.
就像我在立方空间的例子中尝试展示的那样。
And then as soon as they are translated
然后一旦它们被转换
into these formal categorical terms,
用这些形式化的范畴术语来表达，
one can try to take some very different category
可以尝试取一个非常不同的范畴
and apply it there and see what happens.
然后应用到那里看看会发生什么。
So material homotopy theory happens
所谓的材料同伦理论发生在
when one applies this kind of procedure
当将这种程序应用于
to the following category of algebraic equations,
下列代数方程的范畴时，
systems of algebraic equations,
代数方程系统，
which I'm going to describe in a moment.
我一会儿会描述它们。
That's not exactly the standard approach to algebraic geometry,
这并不是代数几何的标准方法，
but that's the most elementary one which I could think of.
但这是我能想到的最基础的方法。
So let's consider the following objects,
所以让我们考虑以下对象，
which we call systems of algebraic equations.
我们称之为代数方程组系统。
So by definition, a system of algebraic equations
由定义，一个代数方程组系统
is the following gadget.
是如下装置。
It's first of all a list of letters
首先是一系列字母
which are called variables of the system,
称为系统的变量，
and second of all some list of polynomials in these variables
其次是一些这些变量的多项式列表
which are called equations of the system.
称为系统的方程式。
So here is an example.
这是一个例子。
There is one variable X
有一个变量 X
and one equation X squared plus one.
以及一个方程 \(X^2 + 1\).
Here is another example.
这是另一个例子。
There are N variables, X1, XN,
有 N 个变量，\(X_1, X_N\)，
and there are no equations whatsoever.
并且没有任何方程。
That's a very important system which is denoted by AN.
那是一个非常重要的系统，记作 \(A_N\)。
Here is a more sophisticated example.
这是一个更复杂的例子。
I'm sorry, I was getting late writing it,
对不起，我写晚了，
and it's not probably very readable.
而且可能不太容易读。
I have N squared variables.
我有 \(N^2\) 个变量。
I'm thinking about them as about entries in a matrix
我把它们当作矩阵中的元素来考虑。
plus one additional variable which I call T.
除此之外，还有一个变量 T。
And I have one equation which says
我有一个方程，说的是
it's the determinant of this matrix times T minus one.
这个矩阵的行列式乘以 T 减一。
Well, it doesn't say anything, but that's my equation.
好吧，这并没有说什么，但这就是我的方程。
That's my polynomial.
这是我的多项式。
And such a system of equations I want to denote by GLN.
而这样的方程系统我希望表示为 GLN。
Now, let's define morphisms.
现在，我们来定义态射。
Oh, I need to say something else.
哦，我还需要说一些其他的事情。
So now I want to try to define
现在我想尝试定义
the category of systems of algebraic equations.
方程系统的范畴。
So what I need first are
首先我需要的是对象，作为对象我会取...
objects, and as objects I will take...
对象，作为对象我会取...
I want to sort of say let's consider
我想说的是让我们考虑
all systems of algebraic equations,
所有代数方程系统，
but that's a bit too many.
但这有点太多了。
So a typical approach is we first choose
因此一个典型的办法是我们首先选择
what kind of coefficients are we going to consider.
我们要考虑什么样的系数。
So let's take some system of coefficients,
那么我们取一些系数系统，
integral numbers or real numbers or complex numbers,
整数或实数或复数，
and consider all systems with the same coefficients.
并考虑具有相同系数的所有系统。
And consider all systems with coefficients
考虑所有带有这种数作为系数的系统。
in this type of numbers.
这些将是我们的范畴中的对象类。
That will be the class of objects of our category.
现在我需要从一个系统到另一个系统的态射。
Now I need morphisms from one system to another.
所以我试着写下来，
So I tried to write it down,
但在投影仪上很难看清楚。
and it's difficult to read on a projector.
因此，通过态射我希望表示变量的变化。
So by morphism I want to mean a change of variables.
所以从变量 x 的一个系统
So a morphism from one system in variables x
到另一个变量 y 的系统的态射
to another system in variables y
将是某种表达变量 y 的方式。
is going to be some way to express variables y
(已与上一条字幕合并)
through variables x, such that the equations
通过变量 x，使得方程在两边近似成立。
sort of are satisfied on both sides.
这种关系在两边都近似满足。
There is some obvious way to compose these things.
这些东西有一种显然的组合方式。
It wasn't I who invented this.
我不是发明这个的人。
I don't know who invented it,
我不知道是谁发明的，
but I read it in a wonderful textbook
但我在一本精彩的教科书里读到过
by Manin on algebraic geometry,
关于代数几何的著作，
which was published in Soviet Union
它在20世纪60年代末期出版于苏联。
in the end of the 60s.
所以这里有一个例子。
So here is an example.
这是一个例子。
Let's consider A0.
让我们考虑 A0。
So remember A0 is...
所以记得 A0 是...
Let me do it this way.
我就用这种方式来做。
A0 is a system of no equations and no variables.
A0 是一个没有方程也没有变量的系统。
So a morphism from such a system
因此，从这样一个系统的态射
would mean that I have to find expressions of my x1, xn
就意味着我必须找到 x1, xn 的表达式
in terms of no variables whatsoever.
用没有任何变量的方式。
So it means I have to replace them by constants,
所以这就意味着我要把它们替换为常数，
and the equations still have to be satisfied.
而方程仍然需要被满足。
So such a morphism is exactly a solution
因此这样的态射正好是一个解。
of my system of equations.
我系统的方程组。
So morphisms from A0 to x
所以从 A0 到 x 的态射
are solutions of the system of equations.
是方程组的解。
Similarly, one can verify that morphisms from x to A0,
同样，可以验证从 x 到 A0 的态射，
there's always only one morphism.
通常只有一个态射。
So these objects An,
因此这些对象 An，
these systems sort of with no equations,
这些系统仿佛没有方程，
they form a cubical object in a very naive sense.
在非常朴素的意义上形成了一个立方体对象。
One can easily build all the maps
可以很容易地构建所有存在的映射
which exist between usual cubes.
哪些在通常的立方体之间存在。
One can build them between these systems.
可以在这些系统之间构建它们。
And so I can use this cubical object
而我可以使用这个立方体对象
to define some kind of homotypic groups
来定义某种同构群
for any system of algebraic equations.
对于任何代数方程系统。
In general, I will get...
一般来说，我会得到...
Sorry, homotypic sets.
抱歉，是同构集。
In general, I will get not quite correct results,
一般来说，我不会得到完全正确的结果，
but there is an example.
但有一个例子。
If I apply it to the system GLN,
如果将其应用于 GLN 系统，
I will actually get very, very reasonable things.
我实际上会得到非常合理的东西。
I will get sets which are called algebraic K groups
我将得到称为代数 K 群的集合
of the original system of coefficients.
原始系数系统的。
And these groups were defined in many difficult ways
而这些群是在过去的几十年中以许多困难的方式定义的。
over the last, I don't know, 40 years.
大概是最近 40 年。
And they're still a source of great many
它们仍然是许多有趣的数学问题和洞察力的来源。
interesting mathematical problems and insights.
这些确实取决于关键点。
This is something which really depends on key.
对于整数，它将与数论和算术有关。
So for integers, it will have something to do
对于复数或实数，
with number theory and arithmetics.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
For complex numbers or real numbers,
there are connections with special functions
与特殊函数有关
such as polylogarism and hyperbolic geometry,
如多项对数和双曲几何，
and I don't know what else.
而我不知道还有其他什么。
So these are very, very interesting groups.
所以这些是非常有趣的群组。
And sort of this is an example of how such a game
而这种例子展示了这样的游戏
can lead us to actually objects
可能会引导我们到一些独立有趣的对象。
which are of independent interest.
因此现在让我展示最后一张幻灯片
So now let me have the last slide
并稍微谈谈哲学问题。
and get a little philosophical.
这就是我看待整体图景的方式。
And so that's how I see the whole picture.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
Let me start with geometry,
让我们从几何开始，
category of topological spaces.
拓扑空间的范畴。
We invent something about this geometrical world
我们用基本的视觉直觉来发明一些关于这个几何世界的东西。
using our basically visual intuition.
我们是通过视觉直观来构建这些概念的。
The notion of pieces comes exclusively
零件的概念完全来自于视觉直观。
from visual intuition.
但我们有些抽象，并将其重新写成范畴论的语言，
We're somehow abstracted and rewrite it
这种语言提供了连接不同概念的方式。
in terms of category theory,
然后我们将其应用于新的情况，
which provides this connecting language.
(已与上一条字幕合并)
And then we apply it in a new situation,
in this case in the situation of algebraic equations,
在这种情况下，在代数方程的情况下，
which is purely algebraic.
这是纯粹的代数。
So what we get is some fantastic way
所以我们得到的是某种奇妙的方法
to translate geometric intuition
将几何直觉
into results about algebraic objects.
转化为关于代数对象的结果。
And that's, from my point of view,
对我来说，
the main fun of doing mathematics.
这就是做数学的主要乐趣。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Applause
鼓掌